Guide to the Michael Grumley Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Michael Grumley papers
1910-1988
1963-1988
YCAL MSS 323
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13
(18 boxes)
The Michael Grumley Papers primarily contain his writings and supporting research material, with a small amount of personal correspondence and personal papers. More than half of the collection consists of his creative writings and drawings, spanning his college years through his career as a freelance author, many of which were not published during his lifetime. The collection holds files on Grumley's published work, including his one novel and his four books on the topics of Atlantis, Sasquatch, sadomasochism, and night workers, in addition to his columns and criticism for periodicals such as the New York Native and the Philadelphia Gay News. The papers also include his daily journals and engagement calendars.
Grumley, Michael
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Michael Grumley Estate on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The Robert Ferro Papers (YCAL MSS 322) holds additional personal and business correspondence addressed to both Grumley and Ferro as well as material related to Grumley's memorial service, which was arranged by Ferro; also filed there are drafts of a few unpublished works coauthored by the couple.
Michael Grumley (1941-1988)
The illustrator and writer Michael Grumley was born in Davenport, Iowa, on July 6, 1941, and raised in nearby Bettendorf, Iowa, with his three brothers Charles, Terry, and Timothy. He attended the University of Denver and Mexico City College before earning a BA degree from the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee in 1964, after which he took a seasonal position with the Johnson's Wax Pavilion at the New York World's Fair. He returned to work at the fair the next summer, and when it closed in October 1965, Grumley applied to City College of the City University of New York for graduate study in literature. He enrolled at CUNY in January in 1966, but transferred in February 1967 to the Writers' Workshop at the University of Iowa, where he studied writing with Kurt Vonnegut and took film courses. While at Iowa Grumley met fellow Workshop student Robert Ferro (1941-1988; MFA 1967), and by semester's end, the two had begun their life together. Known to their friends as "the Ferro-Grumleys," the couple lived primarily on New York's Upper West Side for twenty years, but also spent periods of time in Rome and London. Another favorite place was the Ferro family's oceanfront home in Sea Girt, New Jersey, where they regularly entertained friends and family.
During the early 1980s Grumley worked part-time at Endicott Booksellers, a neighborhood store, otherwise devoting much of his energy to his research and writing projects. Four of his five published books dealt with disparate topics, but all explored alternative theories and lifestyles. The first, Atlantis: the Autobiography of a Search (Doubleday, 1970), was co-written with Robert Ferro, and presented a dual first-person narrative of their trip to the Bahamas in the Ferro family's yacht. His second, also for Doubleday, was There Are Giants in the Earth (1974), a study of legends surrounding Bigfoot (Sasquatch). Grumley provided the text to accompany Ed Gallucci's photographs for Hard Corps: Studies in Leather and Sadomasochism (Dutton, 1977). His After Midnight (Scribner, 1978) profiled a group of people employed on night shifts, including workers in a zoo, hospital, baby powder factory, and on a shrimp boat. Grumley wrote reviews and essays for periodicals such as Stagebill, Philadelphia Gay News, and New York Native, where his weekly column, "Uptown," was regularly featured between 1980 and 1984. Additionally, he contributed illustrations to a number of publications such as Black Men/White Men: a Gay Anthology (Gay Sunshine Press, 1983). His final work, Life Drawing: a novel (Grove Weidenfeld, 1991) was published posthumously.
Michael Grumley and Robert Ferro were affiliated with a literary group known as the Violet Quill, whose seven members, as men writing for men, are regarded as one of the strongest collective voices of the gay male experience in the post-Stonewall era. Authors Christopher Cox, Andrew Holleran, Felice Picano, Edmund White, George Whitmore, Ferro, and Grumley met several times in 1979, 1980, and 1981 to read aloud from their works in progress. Also on the agenda were discussions of how they could work together to promote recognition, acceptance, and publication of gay literature beyond the boundaries of their own community. Of the VQ writers, Michael Grumley and Robert Ferro were the first to die from AIDS-related complications, both in 1988 at age 46, Grumley on April 28 and Ferro on July 11; they were followed by Whitmore in 1989 and Cox in 1990.
Scope and Contents
The Michael Grumley Papers primarily contain his writings and supporting research material, with a small amount of personal correspondence and personal papers. More than half of the collection consists of his creative writings and drawings, spanning his college years through his career as a freelance author, many of which were not published during his lifetime. In addition to his one novel and his four books on the topics of Atlantis, Sasquatch, sadomasochism, and night workers, Grumley wrote columns and criticism for periodicals such as the New York Native and the Philadelphia Gay News. His files hold research notes, contracts, drafts, tear sheets, reviews, and fan mail.
While most of Grumley's writings explored alternative legends and lifestyles, he also composed short works of whimsy for both children and adults. In addition to preparing texts, he drew illustrations for several of his own projects, such as a proposed book on tarot, and created images to accompany other writers' words; also in the collection are more than one hundred of his stylized ink drawings. Equally important are Grumley's set of daily journals and engagement calendars which provide an intimate narrative of the activities, culture, and community of an American writer fully experiencing life in New York, Rome, and London in the 1970s and 1980s, in particular a life lived in the midst of the AIDS epidemic.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence and Personal Papers (1910-1988); II. Writings (1963-1987); and III. Other Papers (1971-1988).
AIDS (Disease); American fiction -- 20th Century; Atlantis (Legendary place); Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- United States; Gay men's writings, American; Geographical myths; Labor movement -- United States -- Case studies; Labor -- United States -- Case studies; Loch Ness monster; Primates -- Folklore; Sasquatch; Violet Quill (Group of writers); Working class -- United States -- Case studies; Yeti; Bimini Islands (Bahamas) -- Description and travel; Italy -- Description and travel -- 20th Century; Appointment books -- United States -- New York -- 20th Century; Diaries -- United States -- New York -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- 20th Century; Illustrations -- United States -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Barbrook, Marguerite, 1903-; Cleaver, Diane; Dinsdale, Tim; Ferro, Robert; Gibson, Morgan, 1929-; Gordon, Robert, 1932-; Gotfryd, Alex; Grumley, Michael; Holiday, F. W. (Frederick William), 1921-1979; Ross, Nancy Wilson, 1901-1986; Turolla, Pino; Iowa Writers' Workshop; New York World's Fair ( 1964-1965 New York, N.Y.)
- Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1910-1988; Series I; 4; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into three subseries: Correspondence; Personal Papers; and Calendars and Journals.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains some correspondence files and a few personal papers, including a set of calendars and daily journals kept by Grumley. Little was retained in the way of personal correspondence; the collection holds just a few letters from members of his family, notably those from his brother Terry who was serving with the Peace Corps in Nicaragua. There are a few letters from the playwright Robert Gordon and a single card from Robert Ferro. Personal Papers includes a folder of horoscope, tarot card, and numerology readings for both Grumley and Ferro, as well as some school, tax, and unemployment records. Notable in the subseries are Grumley's files on the 1964 New York World's Fair (including a typed "diary" made during the fair's final days), and an Italian court invoice for the couple's April 1971 arrest, week-long imprisonment, and trial on a public indecency charge; those traumatic events are fully described in Grumley's daily journal in the following subseries. Also here are papers that record the two public exhibitions of Grumley's drawings, and a resume and arts guide that document his brief turn as a model.
  Perhaps the most important of the personal papers are the twenty-year sets of engagement calendars and daily journals. As they record the activities of the household, Robert Ferro also made notations in the calendars, but they appear to have been kept primarily by Grumley. The journals, which are exclusively in Grumley's hand, in particular provide a compelling narrative of the lives of "the Ferro-Grumleys" and their friends, describing the activities, events, relationships, meals, travels, and, in the 1980s, the incessant presence if symptoms, treatments, hospitalizations, and memorial services, as AIDS began to decimate their community, as well as his own health. Grumley also mentions the meetings of the Violet Quill writers group in March, April, and July 1980, and March 1981, and the literary works featured.
  - Correspondence
    - Barbrook, Marguerite, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Includes snapshot photographs of Grumley and Ferro
    - Boyle, Nichola, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bruning, Fred
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Cimitero degli stranieri acattolici al Testaccio
    - Cimitero degli stranieri acattolici al Testaccio [Protestant Cemetery, Rome], 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Regarding the maintenance of the gravesite of friend David Harker Pelly
    - Cleaver, Diane, 1970-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Doubleday, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes writing samples
    - Ferro, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gibson, Morgan, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes several poems by Grumley
    - Gordon, Robert, 1965-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Grumley family, 1965-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Huenergardt, Margaret
      See: Barbrook, Marguerite
    - Hulme, Mary K. Sergeant, 1975-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ross, Nancy Wilson, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chain letters, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Rejection slips and letters, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters to editors and public officials, 1973-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General correspondence, 1958-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - Personal Papers
    - Address/phone books, loose cards and numbers, circa 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Athol, Massachusetts, clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Business handwriting certificate, 1953
    - Century 21 Exposition, Seattle, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Education records, grade and test reports, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Endicott Booksellers, program notes, 1981-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Exhibition, Galleria 88, Rome, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Exhibition, Leslie Lohman Gallery, New York, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Financial papers, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Fujibloc and print, 1983 Sep (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Health records, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Household inventory, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Horoscope, tarot, and numerology readings, 1970-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Jury duty papers, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Leather pouch holding single dollar bill, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - National Endowment for the Arts, 1977, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - New York World's Fair, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
    - Real estate papers, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Receipt for fine, Rome, Italy, 1977 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Resume, and San Juan arts guide, 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Tax and financial records, 1964-1987 (Box 1, Folder 40-43)
    - Television script, "Claire Ambler", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Travel documents (includes Robert Ferro), 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous ephemera, exhibition brochures, theater programs, etc., 1933-1983 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
    - Miscellaneous images (photographs, postcards, etc.), 1910, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1954-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
    - Notes and ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Calendars and Journals
    The subseries contains a set of engagement and wall calendars, followed by a set of daily journals; both are chronologically arranged. There are two calendars each for the years 1976 and 1977, and there is no calendar for 1983.
    - Calendars, 1966-1987 (Box 2, Folder 53-75)
    - Journals, 1966-1983 (Box 3, Folder 76-91)
    - Journals, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 92-97)
- Writings and Drawings, 1963-1987; Series II; 7.5; (7 boxes)
  The series is organized into three subseries: Articles and Reviews; Books; and Other Writings and Drawings.
  The series contains correspondence and research files supporting Grumley's writing projects, as well as contracts, notes, drafts, reviews, and fan mail pertaining to his published works.
  The first subseries, Articles and Reviews, holds examples of his work for hire, in particular his regular column, "Uptown," published in the New York Native between 1980 and 1984. The collection holds clippings and tear sheets from the paper, as well as a second set of tear sheets onto which Grumley had collaged other texts and images, and enclosed inside personally decorated covers. The Books subseries holds material on Grumley's published work; it includes some correspondence, but mainly holds research notes, drafts, and various proofs and mechanicals. After Midnight (working title "Night People") contains drafts of the full manuscript as well as files on each of the individual chapters, which contain his research material, clippings, photographs, and some correspondence on the personalities profiled. One chapter, "AKA Gloria," a profile of actress Gloria Rossi, was submitted with a National Endowment for the Arts grant application and to New York magazine. Atlantis: the Autobiography of a Search was a collaborative effort between Grumley and Ferro, with each writing alternate chapters. The project files also hold photographs taken by Grumley during their excursion, as well as underwater photographs made by the noted explorer Pino Turolla (1921-1984).
  Other Writings and Drawings is the largest subseries, and spans Grumley's college essays through to the book-length projects he worked on through the 1980s, most of which went unpublished during his lifetime. Some of his early essays were published in Cheshire, the University of Wisconsin's literary journal. A folder of short pieces he labeled "Vonnegut" were apparently submitted to his instructor at Iowa, though they have no annotations or remarks by him. A few of Grumley's writings are autobiographical in nature, such as the essay "I Was a Cast of Thousands," which describes his experiences as an extra in a half-dozen films including The Eyes of Laura Mars (1978) and Ragtime (1981). When Grumley created illustrations for his writings, their presence is noted in the folder listing. A group of folders at the end of the series hold Miscellaneous Drawings and Collages, which are sets of Grumley's stylized line drawings, some of which have collage elements added, as well as individual drawings that appear unrelated to texts or each other; most are not dated.
  - Articles and Reviews
    - Advocate: book review, 1986 Jun 10 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - First Hand: column and illustrations, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - New York Magazine: "Gloria After Midnight", 1978 Feb 27
      See: After Midnight
    - New York Native ("Uptown" column)
      - Correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 100)
      - Typescripts and notes, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
      - Portfolio of tear sheets, 1980-1984
      - Tear sheets, 1981-1985, undated
      - Photocopies of tear sheets, 1982-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Passages: "In Search of Sasquatch" (July 1976), 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Philadelphia Gay News, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Stagebill, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 105-107)
  - Books
    Filed alphabetically by title
    - After Midnight (1978)
      - Outlines, undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
      - Correspondence, contract, royalty reports, 1975-1982 (Box 5, Folder 109)
      - Research files, chapter drafts
        - "Death and Doctor Goodglass", 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 110-113)
        - "Paging Joyce Camel", 1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 114-116)
        - "Still Water", 1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 117-118)
        - "God and Man in the Tenderloin", 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 119-121)
        - "Chicago Ed", 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 122-124)
        - "Among the Exotics", 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 125-129)
        - "Baby Powder", 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 130-132)
        - "AKA Gloria", 1973-1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 133-135)
        - Miscellaneous, 1975-1982 (Box 5, Folder 136-137)
      - Book drafts
        - "Master copy", undated (Box 5, Folder 138)
        - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 6, Folder 139-140)
        - Typescript corrected, undated (Box 6, Folder 141-142)
        - Loose pages and notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 143)
        - "Copy edited manuscript", 1977 (Box 6, Folder 144-145)
      - Dust jacket versions, [1977] (Box 6, Folder 146)
      - Publicity, reviews, and fan mail, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Atlantis: the Autobiography of a Search (1970), by Michael Grumley and Robert Ferro
      - Contracts, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 148)
      - Correspondence
        - Doubleday & Company, 1969-1984 (Box 6, Folder 149-150)
          See also: Doubleday in Series I
        - Turolla, Pino, 1969-1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 151)
        - Miscellaneous, 1969-1978, undated (Box 6, Folder 152)
      - Research materials, expedition notes, miscellaneous articles, 1968-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 153)
      - Prologue, undated (Box 6, Folder 154)
      - Manuscript draft [1], undated (Box 6, Folder 155)
      - Manuscript draft [2], undated (Box 6, Folder 156-157)
      - Photocopies of drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 158-159)
      - Setting copy, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 160-161)
      - Final galley, 1970 Jun 5 (Box 7, Folder 162)
      - Revised galley, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 163)
      - Foundry proof, 1970 Aug 17 (Box 7, Folder 164-165)
      - Miscellaneous draft pages and notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 166)
      - Photographs
        - Contact sheets and negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 167)
        - Slides, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 168)
        - Photographs with captions, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 169)
        - Duplicate photographs, various formats, undated (Box 7, Folder 170-173)
        - Miscellaneous images and stats, 1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 174)
      - Dust jacket, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 175)
      - Publicity and reviews, 1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 176)
        Includes photographs of Grumley and Ferro on "Cavalcade of Books" television show
      - Book excerpt in Chicago Tribune Sunday Magazine, 1971 Feb 14
      - Fan mail, 1970-1977 (Box 7, Folder 177-179)
      - "Atlantis" air sickness bags and salt packet, undated (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Hard Corps: Studies in Leather and Sadomasochism (1977)
      - Correspondence, contracts, royalty reports, 1976-1983 (Box 7, Folder 181-182)
      - Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 183)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 184-186)
      - Miscellaneous loose pages, undated (Box 7, Folder 187)
      - Camera copy, 1977
      - Mechanicals, 1977
      - Galleys, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 188-189)
      - Brownlines, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 190)
      - Signatures with covers, unbound, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 191)
      - Publicity, 1977 Mar 14
      - Fan mail, reviews, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - Life Drawing: a novel (1991)
      - Draft, undated (Box 8, Folder 193)
      - Draft, 1987 May 25 (Box 8, Folder 194-195)
      - "Draft for typist", 1987 Oct (Box 8, Folder 196)
      - "Draft, corrected", undated (Box 8, Folder 197)
      - Draft, undated (Box 8, Folder 198-199)
      - Loose pages, list of edits, miscellaneous material, undated (Box 8, Folder 200)
      - "Life Drawing," in Men on Men: Best New Gay Fiction (1986), 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 201)
    - There Are Giants in the Earth (1974)
      - Correspondence
        - Doubleday & Company, 1973-1981 (Box 8, Folder 202)
        - Sidgwick & Jackson, Ltd., 1974-1979 (Box 8, Folder 203)
        - Miscellaneous, 1973-1977 (Box 8, Folder 204)
      - Research files
        - Notes and drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 205)
        - Printed material, including newspaper clippings, 1970-1987, undated (Box 8, Folder 206-207)
      - Drawings, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 208)
      - Rough draft and notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 209-211)
      - "First draft" [incomplete], undated (Box 8, Folder 212)
      - "Incomplete, with bibliography, index", undated (Box 8, Folder 213-214)
      - "Complete", undated (Box 9, Folder 215-216)
      - Setting copy, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 217-218)
      - Galley, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 219)
      - Foundry proof, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 220)
      - Photographs and negatives, 1977, undated (Box 9, Folder 221)
      - Dust jacket, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 222)
      - Publicity and reviews, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 223)
      - Fan mail and reader responses, 1974-1983 (Box 9, Folder 224-226)
  - Other Writings and Drawings
    - "Acapulco," in Cheshire, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 227)
    - "The Adventures of a Chair," with illustrations, undated (Box 9, Folder 228)
    - "Arab World Cookbook:" illustration, undated (Box 9, Folder 229)
    - "Baby", undated (Box 9, Folder 230)
    - "Beach Book" / "Beach Rites"
      - Outlines, undated (Box 9, Folder 231)
      - Notes and research materials, 1980-1981, undated (Box 9, Folder 232)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 9, Folder 233-235)
    - "Bestiary," with illustrations, 1969-1972, undated (Box 9, Folder 236-241)
    - Black Men / White Men: a Gay Anthology: illustrations, 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - "Books", 1986 May 8 (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - "Brothers" / "Brothering", 1981-1983 (Box 9, Folder 244-245)
    - "Buddy," with illustrations, undated (Box 9, Folder 246)
    - "Caddying", undated (Box 10, Folder 247)
    - "Curious History of Sister Mary Wer-Wolf" / "Sister Sylvana," with illustrations, undated (Box 10, Folder 248-252)
    - "Cybernetta," with illustrations, undated
    - "The Devil at Loch Ness" / "The Dragon of the Lake", 1975-1979 (Box 10, Folder 253-258)
    - "Early on the Delta", undated (Box 10, Folder 259)
    - "The Enchanted Garden" / "The Healing Garden," with illustrations, 1973-1985, undated (Box 10, Folder 260-262)
    - "Fair Game" and "Simple People", undated (Box 10, Folder 263)
    - "A Fool's Tarot," with illustrations, circa 1970 (Box 10, Folder 264)
    - "Georgie" [film proposal], undated (Box 10, Folder 265)
    - "Hill Street Blues," script notes and ideas, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 266)
    - "Hydra", undated (Box 10, Folder 267)
    - "I Was a Cast of Thousands", 1982-1984 (Box 10, Folder 268)
    - "Letter to No Known Address", 1968 (Box 10, Folder 269)
    - "The Love Bug: a Venereal Odyssey," with illustrations, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 270)